Carl Neuberg Papers ca.1880-1956 1940-1956 Mss.Ms.Coll.4
American Philosophical Society
Carl Neuberg Papers
Bulk, 1940-1956
ca.1880-1956
Mss.Ms.Coll.4
American Philosophical Society
10.75 Linear feet
A pioneer biochemist, Carl Neuberg (1877-1956) spent over thirty years of his productive career as a professor at the University of Berlin (1903-1937) and as Director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institutes of Biochemistry and Experimental Therapy. His varied research interests resulted in important contributions to the understanding of fermentation processes, solubility and transport phenomena in cells, the chemistry of carbohydrates, sugars, enzymes, and amino acids, and photochemistry. Neuberg was forced out of his position after the Nazi rise to power, and taking refuge in the United States. For the last several years of his life, he worked at New York University. The Neuberg collection consists of correspondence, lab notebooks, documents, photographs, and reprints, nearly all dating from after Neuberg's departure from Germany in 1940. The correspondence documents Neuberg's late-career work and the contacts he developed with American chemical manufacturers and industries involved in fermentation, as well as the burgeoning post-war relationship between scientific research and the federal dollar. Files for the American Cancer Society, U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, and the U.S. Public Health Service in particular contain useful information for study of the politics and mechanics of government grants.
Neuberg, Carl, b. 1877
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Carl Neuberg was one of Germany's most important biochemists, from intellectual, institutional, and commercial standpoints. His investigations were reflected in over 900 publications covering sugar chemistry, fermentation processes, enzyme chemistry, amino acid studies, and phenomena of biochemical reduction and phosphorylation in living cells. He was the founder and editor of the Biochemische Zeitschrift (1906), and from the early 1920s until 1937 was director of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute for Experimental Therapy and of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute for Biochemistry.
After being ousted by the Hitler regime, Neuberg's odyssey through Holland, Palestine, Iraq, Iran, India, and New Guinea finally brought him to New York in 1940 at the age of sixty-three. With a few exceptions, the Neuberg Papers (correspondence, laboratory notebooks, documents, photographs, and reprints) date from his arrival in America.
According to Neuberg, he had arrived "ten years too late to find a proper position." Relative to other prominent emigre biochemists (Bergmann, Chargaff, Schoenheimer, etc.), Neuberg did not fare well in his new country. The tiny laboratory at New York University and the facilities he later obtained at Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute were inadequate for a substantial research program. He continued to investigate problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes, especially in the pharmaceutical and fermentation industries.
Neuberg also continued his fundamental research in cell chemistry, with moderate support from private and public sources. His studies on solubility and transport phenomena in cells and tissues were relevant to several fields in the life sciences, such as agriculture, nutrition, cytology, and oncology, leading to projects supported by the United States government. The files on government-sponsored research contain a wealth of information -- proposals, contracts, progress reports, and letters -- highlighting the growing linkages between the life sciences, government, and the military during the postwar era.
Throughout his life in the United States, Neuberg remained attached to European science and to international causes in science. Aside from founding the American Society of European Chemists, he maintained correspondence with scientists from other countries, including Japan. Neuberg's correspondence with prominent German chemists (in German) is very informative on postwar German science, issues surrounding the intellectual migration, and Neuberg's misfortune in particular.
Abderhalden, Emil, 1877-1950 ( On differences between American and German science, and on Max Bergmann.) Correspondence (36 items) 1945-1949 German
Adams, Roger, 1889-1971 ( Adams' impressions of postwar Germany.) Correspondence (4 items) 1946-1948 English
American Cancer Society ( Indicative of Neuberg's research in cell chemistry.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1949-1956 English
Anheuser-Busch, Inc. ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the fermentation industry.) Correspondence (8 items) 1942-1956 English
Anschutz, Ludwig, b. 1889 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (34 items) 1947-1955 German
Aron, Hans C. S. ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1942-1955 German
Butenandt, Adolph Friedrich Johann, 1903-1995 ( Documents the strong bond between the two important biochemists, Butenandt and Neuberg. There are references to the prewar era, but much of the correspondence addresses events after the war: Butenandt's tenure at the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute, the state of German science, and Neuberg's plight. These letters are an important source on Butenandt, German science, and the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1947-1956 German
Carbide and Carbon Chemicals Company ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes.) Correspondence (14 items) 1942-1953 English
Deuticke, Hans Joachim ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (26 items) 1951-1956 German
Euler, Hans von, 1873-1964 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (12 items) 1947-1956 German
Federal Yeast Corporation ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the fermentation industry.) Correspondence (5 items) 1943-1956 English
Fromageot, Claude, 1899-1958 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (35 items) 1940-1953 German
Gaffron, H. (Hans) ( On research interests, and technical and social issues.) Correspondence (14 items) 1943-1956 German
Hahn, Otto, 1879-1968 ( On issues related to Neuberg's directorship of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute.) Correspondence (18 items) 1947-1956 German
Hoffmann-La Roche ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the pharmaceutical industry.) Correspondence (24 items) 1944-1954 German
Jacobsohn, Kurt Paul, 1904-1991 ( Scientific, professional, and personal communications. Correspondence between mentor and student. Jacobsohn was a former Ph.D. student of Neuberg's at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute (1926-1929). Some of the letters provide details on Neuberg's escape from Berlin and flight through Palestine before arriving in New York.) Correspondence (5 folders) 1929-1956 German
Kaiser-Wilhelm Gesellschaft zur Forderung der Wisenschaften Correspondence (25 items) 1925-1949 German
Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut fur Biochemie ( Neuberg was the Director of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut fur Biochemie from 1920 to 1937.) Correspondence (1 item) 1927 German
Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut fur Experimentelle Therapie Correspondence (1 item) 1913 German
Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut fur Physikalische Chemie und Elektrochemie Correspondence (1 item) 1916 German
Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut fur Zellphysiologie Correspondence (1 item) 1952 German
Kriegsministerium-Allgemeines Kriegs-Department ( Correspondence with the German War Department. Neuberg contributed materially to the German war effort in 1914-1918 by developing the process of manufacturing glycerol and substitutes through the fermentation of sugar.) Correspondence (5 items) 1917-1918 German
Lederle Laboratories ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the pharmaceutical industry.) Correspondence (7 items) 1943-1949 English
Mazia, Daniel, 1912-1996 ( On Neuberg's difficult times in America.) Correspondence (8 items) 1955-1956 English
Meyerhof, Otto, 1884-1951 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (4 items) 1947-1949 German
Michaelis, Leonor, 1875-1949 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (4 items) 1947-1950 German
Monsanto Chemical Company ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes.) Correspondence (24 items) 1942-1948 English
Nachmansohn, David, 1899-1983 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (7 items) 1947-1955 German
National Grain Yeast Corporation ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the fermentation industry.) Correspondence (4 items) 1942-1949 English
National Sugar Refining Company ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes.) Correspondence (3 items) 1944-1952 English
Carl Neuberg Society for International Scientific Relations ( Materials regarding a society, formerly known as the American Society of European Chemists and Pharmacists, which Neuberg founded.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1947-1980 German
Nord, Friedrich Franz, 1889-1973 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (66 items) 1942-1956 German
Nutrition Foundation ( Indicative of Neuberg's research in cell chemistry.) Correspondence (14 items) 1943-1949 English
Ochoa, Severo, 1905-1993 ( On important aspects of Ochoa's career.) Correspondence (13 items) 1947-1955 English
Rockefeller Foundation ( Grant application and rejection.) Correspondence (2 items) 1941 English
Rohm and Haas Company ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes.) Correspondence (10 items) 1942-1948 English
E. R. Squibb and Sons ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes in the pharmaceutical industry.) Correspondence (3 items) 1948-1953 English
Standard Oil Company ( Problems of relevance to commercial chemical processes.) Correspondence (2 items) 1946-1948 English
Stern, Kurt Guenter ( On interesting professional issues.) Correspondence (28 items) 1943-1956 German
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission ( Grant applications and approval of projects on solubility and metabolism of soil metals.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1949-1953 English
U.S. Department of Agriculture ( Indicative of Neuberg's research in cell chemistry.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1944-1950 English
U.S. Department of the Navy. Office of Naval Research ( Proposals, reports, renewals, and contracts on cell transport projects.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1950-1955 English
U.S. Public Health Service ( On grants for phosphorous compounds and solubility in cells.) Correspondence (8 folders) 1943-1955 English
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter), 1883-1971 Correspondence (1 item) 1951 English
Warburg, Otto Heinrich, 1883-1970 ( Potentially informative correspondence on postwar German science and issues surrounding the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (50 items) 1948-1956 German
Wieland, H. (Heinrich), b. 1877 ( In the 1930s Wieland openly opposed the Nazi regime and supported his Jewish colleagues. One of them was Carl Neuberg, who in 1937 was fired from his post as director of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute for Biochemistry. Contains long letters about German and American colleagues, German and American chemistry, and exchanges about the effects of the war.) Correspondence (28 items) 1946-1955 German
Additional Biographical Notes:
Adolph F. J. Butenandt made most of his seminal discoveries in reproductive biochemistry in the 1930s, while serving as director of the organic chemical laboratories at the University of Tubingen. During that decade he isolated the female sex hormone estrone, the male hormone androsterone, and the female hormone progesterone. Applying sensitive microanalyses, Butenandt deduced the chemical formula of androsterone and predicted the structure of a related compound that was synthesized shortly after. He was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1939, but was forced to refuse it by the Hitler regime, he did not actually receive it until 1949.
In 1936 Butenandt was appointed director of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute for Biochemistry in Berlin, replacing his friend and colleague Carl Neuberg, who had been ousted by the Nazis. Butenandt helped him set up a short-lived underground laboratory in a different part of Berlin, and remained a friend and loyal supporter until Neuberg's death in 1956.
Heinrich O. Wieland spent his student and research career at the University of Munich. His diverse researches in organic chemistry drew students from many countries; several Americans obtained advanced training in his laboratory. His most important investigations (1910s) centered on elucidating the molecular structures of bile acids, showing them to be steroid in nature. As the appreciation for the importance of steroids in reproductive physiology and in nutrition increased during the 1920s, the contributions of Wieland assumed far greater significance. He was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1927.
Separated Materials note
Neuberg's reprints and a collection of books have been transferred to the Department of Printed Materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Carl Neuberg's daughter, Irene Forrest, June 1980.
Scope and Contents note
The disruptions to the life and career of the biochemist, Carl Neuberg, exacted the toll on his papers. The 10.75 linear feet of correspondence, research notes, and photographs that survives is heavily skewed toward the last fifteen years of a long and distinguished career, representing the period between 1942 and 1956 when he was employed at New York University and in retirement. Despite the relative paucity of material for earlier periods of Neuberg's life, the collection offers interesting insights into the experiences and struggles of a Jewish German émigreé scientist to establish himself in American academia.
With the exception of correspondence with his friend Kurt Jacobson in Portugal (5 folders, 1929-1956), a few German industries (4 folders, ca. 1916-1945), the Kaiser Wilhelm Society and Institutes (5 folders, ca. 1913-1952), and the German War Department (2 folders, 1916) the collection has little to offer for Neuberg's pre-war years. Some of post-war correspondence, however, reveals some of the trauma he experienced, and some of his hardships leading up. The letters between Neuberg and Karl Thomas ("Briefe nach 1945") and Kurt Jacobson provide details on Neuberg's escape from Berlin and flight through Palestine before arriving in New York. The letters with Thomas, in particular, give a spare, but moving account of the hardships both chemists faced during and after the war, as Thomas adjusted to life in the new Germany and Neuberg to life in America. Neuberg's impression of American science was unflattering, reflecting his frustrations:
Neuberg's continuing research in cell chemistry, sustained by small grants from public and private sources, eventually generated some support from the United States government. The files on government-sponsored research contain a wealth of information -- proposals, contracts, progress reports, and letters -- highlighting the growing link between the life sciences, government, and the military during the late 1940s and early 1950. Of particular interest in this regard are the materials relating to: the American Cancer Society (5 folders, 1949-1956); the Nutrition Foundation (1943-1945); the Rockefeller Foundation (1941); U.S. Atomic Energy Commission (3 folders, 1949-1953; grant applications and approval of projects on solubility and metabolism of soil metals); U.S. Department of Agriculture (2 folders, 1944-1950); Office of Naval Research (4 folders, 1950-1955, proposals, reports, renewals, and contracts on cell transport projects); and the U.S. Public Health Service (8 folders, 1943-1955, on grants for phosphorous compounds and solubility in cells).
Throughout his life in the United States, Neuberg remained attached to European science and to international causes in science. In addition to his contacts made through the American Society of European Chemists (1 folder, 1948-1954), which he helped found and which changed its name to the Carl Neuberg Society for International Relations (all items in the collection are filed under the new name), Neuberg maintained fairly extensive contact with scientists from other countries, including Japan. His correspondence with prominent German chemists (in German) is informative on postwar German science, issues surrounding the intellectual migration, and Neuberg's misfortunes in particular.
Series I. Correspondence ca.1880-1956 9 linear feet
Series II. Notebooks 1933-1955 1.5 linear feet
Series III. Miscellaneous 1915-1956 0.25 linear feet
Biographical/Historical note
To say that Carl Neuberg (1877-1956) was a pioneer in biochemistry is to understate the case: he coined the term. Born in Hanover, Germany, on July 29, 1877, to the Jewish merchant, Julius Sandel Neuberg and his wife Alma (Niemann), Neuberg studied chemistry under Virchow at the University of Berlin, receiving his Dr. Phil. in 1900. Appointed to the Pathological Institute of the University, Neuberg rose through the academic ranks from Privatdozent in 1903 to Titularprofessor (1906), before becoming head of the Tierphysiologisches Institut at the University from 1909-1913 and simultaneously full professor at the Landwirtschaftliche Hochschule in Berlin.
The major achievements of Neuberg's early career included the elucidation of solubility and transport phenomena in cells, the chemistry of carbohydrates and sugars, photochemistry, and the discovery of the different forms of fermentation. As early as 1912, he also devoted attention to the chemistry of amino acids and enzymes, and in 1916, he discovered hydrotropy, which he considered one of his most important discoveries. Neuberg contributed materially to the German war effort in 1914-1918 by developing the process of manufacturing glycerol and substitutes through the fermentation of sugar.
Neuberg's influence on the emergence of the field of biochemistry was profound. He helped establish the Biochemische Zeitschrift in 1906 and edited 278 volumes over the next thirty years. The nomenclature in the field bears similar traces of Neuberg's ingenuity, including the terms phosphorylation, dismutation, desmolysis, and co-enzyme.
Neuberg's increasing status during the 1910s and 1920s brought him a steady increase in administrative power. In 1913, he was recognized with an appointment as Second Director at the prestigious new Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Experimental Therapy, headed by August von Wasserman, and his promotion to Professor (1916) and full Professor (1919) at the University of Berlin followed in short order. Neuberg accrued a range of other responsibilities at the same time as he became Director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Biochemistry in 1920, of the Institute for Experimental Therapy upon Wasserman's death in 1923, and adding the directorship of the Forschungsstelle des Deutschen Rechies für Chemie des Tabaks in 1928.
With the rise to power of the Nazis, Neuberg initially believed his services during the First World War would afford him some protection. In 1937, however, he was driven out of his posts by the Nazis. Only two days before the war broke out, a friend in military circles issued Neuberg a pass to leave, with the intention of assuming a position offered to him at the University of Jerusalem. Landing in Amsterdem, he worked to raise money for his passage, and with the assistance of his old colleague Claude Fromageot, reached Palestine. Neuberg resumed his monumental wartime peregrinations in 1941, and a dramatic passage through Iraq, Iran, India, and New Guinea, he arrived at New York University in February 1941,with little more than a pair of valises to his name.
Already nearing the standard age of retirement, Neuberg lamented that he had arrived "ten years too late to find a proper position" in the United States, and certainly he fared poorly relative other displaced scholars, such as Max Bergmann and Erwin Chargaff. The miniscule laboratory he occupied at the university from 1941-1950 and his inadequate pay were inadequate to support a substantial research program. "Lieber Herr College Thomas," he wrote to an old colleague in Germany, "Sie sehen in Amerika ist fuer unsereinen nicht das Paradies.... Jetzt bin ich eine alter immigrierter Hund, der nur mit einem Handkoefferchen angekommen ist, Emigrant bin ich eigentlich nicht, sondern nur einfach herausgeworfen." To his old colleague Maria Kobel he complained "Der Titel Research-Professor ist eine Verbraemung des Nichts."
Neuberg nevertheless succeeded in securing important contacts with the pharmaceutical and fermentation industries over the next decade, and like many of his peers, his late career maps out the increasing role played by the federal government and industry in the post-war years. In 1950, he spent a year as visiting lecturer at the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute, and he traveled to Germany in 1952 to deliver lectures on biochemistry, receiving honorary degrees and awards along the way.
Over the course of his career, Neuberg contributed to over 900 publications, including work on the chemistry of sugars, fermentation, enzymes, and amino acids. He considered his most important work to lie in the discovery of carboxylase, the different forms of fermentation, the artificial production of glycerol, and the discovery of pyro-, meta- and polyphosphatases. His work on solubility and transport phenomena had broad applicability in the life sciences, including to agriculture, nutrition, cytology, and oncology.
Neuberg was the recipient of honorary degrees from the universities of Breslau, Danzig, Palermo, Edinburgh, and Berlin, and he was recipient of Emil Fischer Scheele, Berzelius, Delbrück, Leblanc, and Pasteur medals. He died at home in New York in 1956.
American Cancer Society.; Anschütz, Ludwig; Antoniani, Claudio, 1899-; Aron, Hans, 1881-; Auhagen, Ernst; Bloch-Frankenthal, Leah; Butenandt, Adolf, 1903-; Carl Neuberg Society for International Scientific Relations; Collatz, Herbert, 1902-; Deuticke, Hans; Durig, Arnold, 1872-; Euler, Hans von, 1873-1964; Feigl, Fritz, 1891-; Fodor, Andor, 1884-; Fromageot, Claude, 1899-; Gaffron, Hans, 1902-; Hahn, Otto, 1879-1968; Hofmann, Eduard, 1897-; Kaiser Wilhelm Institut fur Biochemie; Kluyver, A. J., (Albert Jan), 1888-1956; Maengwyn-Davies, Gertrude, 1910-; May, Albert von; Nachmansohn, David, 1899-; New York University; Nord, Friedrich Franz, 1889-1973; Ochoa, Severo, 1905-; Rose, William C.; Schoenebeck, Otto von; Sobatka, Harry H.; Telschow, Ernst, 1889-; Thomas, Karl, 1883-; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission.; United States. Public Health Service.; Virtanen, A. I., (Artturi Ilmari), 1895-1973; Warburg, Otto Heinrich, 1883-1970; Wieland, H., (Heinrich), b. 1877; Windaus, Adolf, 1876-1960; Windisch, Fritz, 1898-; Wolfrom, Melville Lawrence, 1900-1960; Biochemistry.; Chemical industry -- United States.; Federal aid to research--United States; Fermentation; Germany--History--1945-1955; Jewish scientists; Laboratory notes; Photographs; Political refugees; Sugars; World War, 1939-1945
- Series I. Correspondence, 1970-1975; 3 lin. feet
  Scope and Contents note